<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 10000 Hours | Programming the City]]></title>
  <link href="http://rosiehoyem.github.io/blog/categories/10000-hours/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rosiehoyem.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-21T13:47:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rosiehoyem.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rosie Hoyem]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10,000 Hours of Practice]]></title>
    <link href="http://rosiehoyem.github.io/blog/2013/07/28/10000-hours-of-practice/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T15:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rosiehoyem.github.io/blog/2013/07/28/10000-hours-of-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>10,000 Hours of Practice</h1>

<p>In Malcolm Gladwell&rsquo;s 2008 best seller, <a href="http://gladwell.com/outliers/">Outliers: The Story of Success</a>, he presents his research and conclusions on a common characteristic among successful people. A lot has to do with timing, luck&mdash;being in the right place at the right time. These things matter too, but practice&mdash;a lot of practice in the craft of choice, is a fundamental requirement to seize the opportunities that serendipity may present.</p>

<p>Even more than 10,000 hours, Gladwell emphasizes that, for those who become true masters of their art, practice ceases to be a chore. It becomes a joy, an obsession, and the central focus of the practitioners life. Work without passion, no matter how many hours logged, will not result in true mastery.</p>

<p>People like to argue about the necessity of this 10,000 hour rule. I have no intention of logging hours towards my goal of becoming a master at my craft. My intention here is to document how I learn to fall in love with my craft, how I frame it in the context of my life to become a passion and a joy, not work that pays my bills.</p>

<p>This is the same philosophy my web development program has chosen. (This is why I chose them.) A quote Avi Flombaum, Dean of <a href="http://flatironschool.com/">Flatiron School</a> used in a recent post that outlines their teaching style captures this spirit perfectly:</p>

<blockquote><p>If you want to build a ship, don’t drum up the men to gather wood, divide the work, and give orders. Instead, teach them to yearn for the vast and endless sea.</p>

<ul>
<li>Antoine de Saint-Exuprey</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
